Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.14
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Campaign for U.S. Senate, 1991; XIV.
  - Schedules and Events, 5.
    - Events
      - Meeting with the Christian Action Council and interview with WDAC Christian Broadcasting Radio, Lancaster, October 1, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 4)
      - USAir Competitive Aviation Hearing, testimony regarding "Pittsburgh-Italy Air Service," Washington, DC, October 1, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 5)
      - Inner Circle Caucus Reception, remarks, Philadelphia, October 1, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 6)
      - Presidential Luncheon Fundraising Event with President Bush, Pittsburgh, October 2, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 7)
      - National Republican Senatorial Committee, Senatorial Trust meeting, remarks, Washington, D.C., October 3, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 8)
      - Drexel Hill Middle School, classroom visit and press announcement on America 2000, Drexel Hill, October 4, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 9)
      - Tour of Collingdale Community Center, Drexel Hill, October 4, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 10)
      - Photo-op with the Pennsylvania Restaurant Association, Philadelphia, October 4, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 11)
      - Knights of Columbus Mass at St. Peter's Cathedral, Scranton, October 6, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 12)
      - Meeting with the Specialty Steel Industry Leaders, Pittsburgh, October 7, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 13)
      - Pittsburgh Press Editorial Board meeting, Pittsburgh, October 7, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 14)
      - Visit to Western Pennsylvania Foundation's Caring for Children headquarters, Pittsburgh, October 7, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 15)
      - Tour of Indiana County Courthouse, Indiana, October 7, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 16)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception, Pittsburgh, October 7, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 17)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee (TSC) breakfast hosted by Mayer Mitchell, Washington, DC, October 8, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 18)
      - Veterans Coalition Endorsement, Philadelphia, October 8, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 19)
      - International Brotherhood of Painters Leadership meeting, Philadelphia, October 8, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 20)
      - Disabilities Community and ADA tribute to the Thornburghs, Washington, DC, October 8, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 21)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception hosted by the Senate Republican Leadership, Washington, DC, October 8, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 22)
      - Republican Senatorial Presidential Roundtable breakfast, Washington, DC, October 9, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 23)
      - Meeting with the Pennsylvania Business Roundtable executive committee, Harrisburg, October 9, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 24)
      - Meeting with Harrisburg Patriot News editorial board, Harrisburg, October 9, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 25)
      - Meeting with Pennsylvania Builders Association, Harrisburg, October 9, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 26)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception hosted by the Butler Country Club, Butler, October 9, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 27)
      - Interview with Fred Honsberger, KDKA Radio, Pittsburgh, October 9, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 28)
      - Victory '91 breakfast with Secretary Kemp, Conshohocken, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 29)
      - Conshohocken Economic Development Corporation, Enterprise Zone press conference, Conshohocken, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 30)
      - Meeting with PA Medical Political Action Committee (PAC), Strasburg, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 31)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee luncheon hosted by Marilyn Lewis, Strasburg, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 32)
      - Farmers for Thornburgh endorsement, Millersville, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 33)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee meeting with Drinker, Biddle & Reath lawyers, Philadelphia, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 34)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception hosted by the Binswangers, Philadelphia, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 35)
      - Arcola Intermediate School's US Department of Education Excellence Award Recognition Ceremony, Morristown, October 10, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 36)
      - Meetings with Jewish Federation of Greater Philadelphia, Philadelphia, October 11, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 37)
      - Fundraising Luncheon with Vice President Quayle, Harrisburg, October 11, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 38)
      - Pennsylvania Pro-Life Annual Conference, White Haven, October 12, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 39)
      - "Hello Columbus 1992" ceremony, Norristown, October 12, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 40)
      - Homecoming dinner in honor of American Legion Commander, Dominic DiFrancesco, Harrisburg, October 12, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 41)
      - Church service at Wayland Temple Baptist Church, Philadelphia, October 13, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 42)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception hosted by Chuck and Dottebob Andes, Villanova, October 13, 1991 (Box 922, Folder 43)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception and dinner, Los Angeles, CA, October 14, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 1)
      - Allegheny Ludlum's Specialty Steel Plant, demonstrations and trade policy announcement, Vandergrift, October 15, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 2)
      - American Association of Retired Persons (AARP) Volunteer Leadership meeting, candidates forum, Harrisburg, October 16, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 3)
      - Pennsylvania Baptist State Convention, King of Prussia, October 16, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 4)
      - Chester County Republican Gala, Kimberton, October 16, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 5)
      - James Weldon Johnson Homes, tour with Barbara Bush, Philadelphia, October 17, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 6)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee fundraising luncheon with Barbara Bush, Philadelphia, October 17, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 7)
      - Montgomery County Republican Committee Annual Fall Dinner, Pottstown, October 18, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 8)
      - Mass at St. Mary's Catholic Church, Wilkes-Barre, October 20, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 9)
      - Northampton County GOP Rally, Pen Argyl, October 20, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 10)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception hosted by Tom Decker and Frank Wright, Villanova, October 20, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 11)
      - Northeast Tier Ben Franklin Technology Center, press announcement, Bethlehem, October 21, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 12)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee fundraising breakfast hosted by Nick DeBenedictis, John Boyer and the Pennsylvania Leadership Conference, Valley Forge, October 21, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 13)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee luncheon with Education Secretary Lamar Alexander, Lehigh University, Bethlehem, October 21, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 14)
      - Meeting with Allentown Morning Call editorial board, Allentown, October 21, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 15)
      - Delaware Republican Committee, reception and dinner, Springfield, October 21, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 16)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee breakfast hosted by Karen and Rick Pfeffer, Altoona, October 22, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 17)
      - Meeting with Altoona Mirror editorial board, Altoona, October 22, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 18)
      - Meeting with Centre County Republican leaders, State College, October 22, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 19)
      - Meeting with the Centre Daily Times editorial board, State College, October 22, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 20)
      - Stardyne, Inc., tour and press availability, Johnstown, October 22, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 21)
      - Meeting with Pittsburgh Post Gazette editorial board, Pittsburgh, October 23, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 22)
      - Public Affairs Forum Luncheon; and Pittsburgh Chamber of Commerce, reception and dinner, Pittsburgh, October 23, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 23)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee reception, Greensburg, October 23, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 24)
      - Philadelphia labor unions endorsements, Philadelphia, October 24, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 25)
      - Editorial board meetings with Philadelphia Inquirer and Philadelphia Daily News, Philadelphia, October 24, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 26)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee fundraising reception hosted by Herb Collins, Boston, MA, October 24, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 27)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee breakfast, New York, NY, October 25, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 28)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee fundraising luncheon hosted by Gene Roth, Wilkes-Barre, October 25, 1991 (Box 923, Folder 29)
      - Classroom visit with Bishop Hoban High School students, Wilkes-Barre, October 25, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 1)
      - Lackawanna County Republican Committee Pre-Election reception and dinner, Peckville, October 25, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 2)
      - Meeting with Scranton Times editorial board, Scranton, October 25, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 3)
      - White Ribbons against Pornography rally, Harrisburg, October 26, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 4)
      - Meeting with Passyunk Avenue civic leaders and tour, Philadelphia, October 26, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 5)
      - 8th National Asian-American Convention sponsored by Asian-American Voters Coalition, Philadelphia, October 26, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 6)
      - Republican Senatorial Inner Circle welcoming reception, Washington, DC, October 27, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 7)
      - Allegheny County Black Republican Council breakfast, Pittsburgh, October 28, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 8)
      - Live interview with WTAE-TV, "Good Day Pittsburgh" noon broadcast, Pittsburgh, October 28, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 9)
      - Rosslyn Farms Community Center, congressional reform announcement, Pittsburgh, 5/3/2004 (Box 924, Folder 10)
      - Pennsylvania Hispanic leaders endorsement, Philadelphia, October 28, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 11)
      - Laborers Local 332 Candidates Night, Philadelphia, October 28, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 12)
      - Interview with Jack Holcomb of WEEU Radio and meeting with Reading Eagle editorial board, Reading, October 29, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 13)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee breakfast fundraiser hosted by Joe Welch, Reading, October 29, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 14)
      - Tour of the R.M. Palmer Co., Reading, October 29, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 15)
      - Tour of Rising Sun Avenue and Foxchase Neighborhood, Philadelphia, October 29, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 16)
      - Meeting with Chester County Anti-Tax and Pro-Family leaders, Malvern, October 29, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 17)
      - Philadelphia Republican City Committee fall reception, Philadelphia, October 29, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 18)
      - Interview with WWDB Talk Radio Call-In Show, Philadelphia, October 30, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 19)
      - Meeting, tour, and press availability at Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, October 30, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 20)
      - Upper Darby Senior Center "Seniors Supporting Thornburgh" announcement, Upper Darby, October 30, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 21)
      - Meet Montgomery County voters at the Ardmore Suburban Square Shopping Center, Ardmore, October 30, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 22)
      - Meeting with American Street Corridor Business Association, economic development program announcement and tour of the American Street Enterprise Zone, Philadelphia, October 31, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 23)
      - Midfield Terminal Construction Site, economic development program announcement and tour, Pittsburgh, October 31, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 24)
      - Meeting with United Jewish Federation of Pittsburgh Board of Directors, Pittsburgh, October 31, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 25)
      - Interview with Fred Honsberger, KDKA Radio, October 31, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 26)
      - Visit with voters outside Pittsburgh Penguins game, Pittsburgh, October 31, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 27)
      - Pittsburgh Fraternal Order of Police endorsement, Pittsburgh, November 1, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 28)
      - Tour of Erie Business District, Erie, November 1, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 29)
      - Lehigh County Republican Committee fall reception, Allentown, November 1, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 30)
      - Bucks County Republican Committee Fall Dinner, Bensalem, November 1, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 31)
      - PA Special Olympics Fall Festival, Villanova, November 2, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 32)
      - Anti-Crime Press Conference with Senator Arlen Specter, Philadelphia, November 2, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 33)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee rally, Scranton, November 2, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 34)
      - "Sons of Italy" Mass at Peter and Paul Cathedral in honor of Mayor Rizzo, Philadelphia, November 3, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 35)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee rally with Representative Gallen, Reading, November 3, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 36)
      - "Rizzocrats for Thornburgh" rally, South Philadelphia, November 3, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 37)
      - Health Care press announcement, Pittsburgh, November 4, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 38)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee rally, Lancaster, November 4, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 39)
      - Election Day--visits to Pittsburgh polling places, Pittsburgh, November 4, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 40)
      - Election Day--Thornburgh for Senate Committee Election Night celebration, Pittsburgh, November 5, 1991 (Box 924, Folder 41)
  - Candidate Thornburgh's Files, 6.
    During the 1991 Campaign for Senate, Thornburgh kept, as for all other campaigns and offices he held, a personal collection of materials known here as " Candidate Thornburgh's files." These are the working files kept close at hand for, in this case, the candidate's ready use and reference. These files of convenience and contain materials that are, in many cases, a condensed version of other campaign matters, and many of which have annotations and notes by Thornburgh.
    "Candidate Thornburgh's files" are organized as follows: 1) "The Campaign," a general section of material containing "core" campaign materials, including speeches (and notes), schedules, media materials, debate preparation, polling data, and others, all arranged roughly by the type of material; 2) Fundraising materials and various finance reports; 3) Issue research, including specialty steel, health care reform, "Dick Thornburgh's Agenda for the 90s," and research on opponent Harris Wofford; 4) Clippings, including the Senate race, Pennsylvania, and post-election clippings (and notes).
    - The Campaign
      - Resignation letter to President Bush regarding Thornburgh's intention to run for U.S. Senate, August 9, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 1)
      - Announcement speech and notes, August 29-30, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 2)
      - "Stump speech" outline and notes, September, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 3)
      - Concession speech and notes, November 5, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 4)
      - Campaign mailings to family and close friends, August-October, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 5)
      - Thornburgh's campaign notes, to-do lists, contacts and staff information, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 6)
      - Media, including advertisements and consultant information, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 7)
      - Issue clippings and articles, May-November, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 8)
      - Telephone logs and notes, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 9)
      - Pennsylvania Association of Broadcasters, debate between Wofford and Thornburgh, Thornburgh's notes, October 18, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 10)
      - Polling data, April-October, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 11)
      - Dick and Ginny Thornburgh's weekly schedules, tentative and confirmed (annotated), September 2-November 4, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 12)
      - Personal notes and correspondence, August-November, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 13)
      - Lawsuit, Trinsey v. Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, et al., U.S. Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit, Docket Nos. 91-1490 and 91-1491, August 6, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 14)
      - Pennsylvania issue updates, 1987-April, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 15)
      - U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) issues and updates, 1989-1991 (Box 925, Folder 16)
    - Fundraising
      - Presidential Salute to Dick Thornburgh fundraiser, attendees list, September 3, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 17)
      - Thornburgh for Senate fundraiser, remarks by President Bush, Philadelphia, PA, September 12, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 18)
      - Richard Thornburgh Breakfast, attendees list, Washington, DC, October 3, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 19)
      - Fundraising Committee correspondence and memoranda from Evans Rose to Thornburgh, 1987-1991 (Box 925, Folder 20)
      - Senate Public Financial Disclosure information and reports, August-November, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 21)
      - Federal Election Commission (FEC) reports regarding Thornburgh's work at Kirkpatrick & Lockhart (K&L), and other materials, September-November, 1991 (Box 925, Folder 22)
      - Campaign debt case: U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, Karl Rove v. Richard Thornburgh, Docket No. 93-8451, ca. 1993 (Box 926, Folder 1)
    - Campaign Positions and Research
      - "Dick Thornburgh's Agenda for the 90s", October 28, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 2)
      - "Thornburgh Announces 14-Point Plan for Affordable Health Care", October, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 3)
      - Affordable health care, related news clippings, October, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 4)
      - Specialty steel industry, October 22, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 5)
      - Wofford, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 6)
    - News Clippings, Notes and Memoranda
      - Regarding U.S. Senate, April-September, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 7)
      - Regarding Senate campaign and race, August 20-October 1, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 8)
      - Thornburgh annotated articles and staff memoranda, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 9)
      - Thornburgh "special" Pennsylvania clippings and annotated articles, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 10)
      - Post election, including election results, and Thornburgh's notes, November-December, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 11)
      - Pennsylvania clippings, 1988-1991 (Box 926, Folder 12-13)
      - Miscellaneous, 1987-1992 (Box 926, Folder 14)
      - Post election material regarding Wofford and health insurance issue, 1991-1994 (Box 926, Folder 15)
  - Ginny Thornburgh's Files, 7.
    As usual, Ginny Thornburgh was an active campaigner on behalf of the husband's quest for the Pennsylvania U.S. Senate seat. Her files here consist of her schedules and event files and include her resume at the time.
    - Event Files
      - September-November, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 16-27)
      - Confirmed Events, May-September, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 28)
      - Prospective Events, September-October, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 29)
    - Campaign Files
      - Thornburgh Campaign Names, September-October, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 30)
      - County Chairmen phone list, October 9-24, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 31)
      - Thornburgh for Senate Committee Travel Policy and Expense Report, undated (Box 926, Folder 32)
      - Ginny Thornburgh resume, August, 1991 (Box 926, Folder 33)
  - Issue Research, 8.
    During the campaign, the daunting job of research fell solely to Harold Miller, who had served as a Director, Office of Policy Development, while Thornburgh was Governor. Since Thornburgh was running for office in a state which he had left only four years previously with a 72% approval rating, a major campaign strategy related to his notable past accomplishments. Harold Miller's familiarity with Thornburgh's gubernatorial record well equipped him for the task.
    In addition to information about Thornburgh's past record, the 1991 campaign issue files also include some "administrative" campaign files, such as those related to media contacts and Thornburgh's ongoing campaign positions. It should be noted, too, that Miller also provided opposition research on Harris Wofford, Thornburgh's opponent, and answered the questionnaires, most of which are available in a separate section by that name. Due to Miller's unique organization of his detailed and extensive files, researchers should note that the best approach to using them is to search on a topic of interest. Important information may be overlooked if one simply browses this valuable group of materials.
    The issue research files are organized as follows: 1) Thornburgh's pre-gubernatorial record, research and documentation, which includes information on achievements and initiatives when Thornburgh served as U.S. Attorney, 1969-1975; 2) Research on Pennsylvania issues, including Thornburgh's gubernatorial record, which includes a large amount of material on issues relating to budget and taxes, education, arts, economic development, cost cutting, housing, etc; 3) Research on federal issues and Thornburgh's Attorney General record, including the Bank of Credit Commerce International (BCCI) case, Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), and Savings and Loan (S and L) scandals; 4) Campaign research, including five sections of material entitled: administrative materials, media, Thornburgh's campaign positions, endorsements, and miscellaneous. Together they document the major efforts of the campaign, including volunteers, commercials and advertisements, and endorsements; 5) Research on Governor Casey and his gubernatorial record, which includes Casey's campaign and years as governor of Pennsylvania, his administrative goals and priorities. This was relevant information since Wofford had been a member of Casey's cabinet; 6) Issue files, including research material that is generally separate from those specific categories mentioned above; 7) Campaign controversies; and 8) Campaign clippings regarding the Senate race.
    - Thornburgh's Pre-Gubernatorial Record: Research and Documentation
      - Position papers issued by Thornburgh, Republican candidate for U.S. House of Representatives, November, 1966 (Box 927, Folder 1)
      - Death penalty, letter from Thornburgh, United States Attorney, to the Attorney General, January 25, 1977 (Box 927, Folder 2)
      - Thornburgh's achievements as United States Attorney, 1969-1975 (Box 927, Folder 3)
      - Articles written by Thornburgh, 1966-1967 (Box 927, Folder 4)
    - Research on Pennsylvania Issues, including Thornburgh's Gubernatorial Record
      - Congressional voting records from various groups during Governor Thornburgh's first term, 1979-1982 (Box 927, Folder 5)
      - Status report on 1979-1980 legislation, December 30, 1980 (Box 927, Folder 6)
      - Status report, legislative priorities in Governor's 1979 message, January 1, 1985 (Box 927, Folder 7)
      - Status report on 1981-1982 legislation (Box 927, Folder 8)
      - Selected comparisons and zingers! regarding New York and Pennsylvania, 1984-1986 (Box 927, Folder 9)
      - Program policy guidelines (PPGs) for 1987-1988 departmental budget requests, September 2, 1986 (Box 927, Folder 10)
      - Mental health/mental retardation (MH/MR) block grants and initiatives, July 3, 1984 (Box 927, Folder 11)
      - Office of Vocational Rehabilitation (OVR) for Pennsylvania, December 6, 1982 (Box 927, Folder 12)
      - Options for improving rural health care in Pennsylvania, analysis and memorandum from Walt Plosila, March 19, 1982 (Box 927, Folder 13)
      - Summary of GAO report on expanded home care services for the elderly, January 31, 1983 (Box 927, Folder 14)
      - H.B. 1901, regarding mandatory alcohol, drug abuse and mental health insurance coverage, August, 1983-November, 1984 (Box 927, Folder 15)
      - H.B. 1901, studies on mental health insurance coverage, ca. 1984 (Box 927, Folder 16)
      - Local Government Commission's "Financially Distressed Municipalities Act," includes S.B. 1714, S.B. 1143, S.B. 1249, August-November, 1986 (Box 927, Folder 17)
      - Human services, minutes of the Department of Public Welfare state/county human service delivery issues policy meetings, September, 1984-March, 1986 (Box 927, Folder 18)
      - Human services, County Human Service Directors meetings, October, 1984-September, 1985 (Box 927, Folder 19)
      - Human services, initiatives and concept papers regarding the needy, March-July, 1986 (Box 927, Folder 20)